A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Hospital, Administrative Correspondence, Series 2 FA837
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Hospital, Administrative Correspondence, Series 2
1906-1968
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
Cole, Rufus
FA837
3 Cubic Feet 2 boxes and 2 packages
Actual extent is unknown.
Arrangement
The Rockefeller University records, Hospital is arranged in four series: Series 1: General Files. Series 2: Administrative Correspondence. Series 3: Subject Files. Series 4: Collected Reprints.
Series 3 is currently closed to scholarly research pending further processing.
File Plan note
Former Classificaiton: I 430-2
Other Finding Aids
FA228 Rockefeller University records, Hospital, General Files, Series 1.
FA838 Rockefeller University records, Hospital, Subject Files, Series 3.
FA909 Rockefeller University records, Hospital, Collected Reprints, Series 4.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Conditions Governing Access note
This material is open for scholarly research.
Medical research; Hospitals; Medical education; Operations management; Medicine, Preventive; Medical technology; Medical sciences; Medical care; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University; Cole, Rufus
- Administrative correspondence, 2
  - Rufus Cole, 1906-1937 1938-1953
    Scope and Contents note
    Bibliography; photographs, some biographical items.
    Consists primarily of administrative correspondence between Rufus Cole, Director of RIMR Hospital and Simon Flexner and Business Managers. Includes many holographs.
    Correspondence includes letters between Rufus Cole and Jerome D. Greene (1910-October 1912) dealing with details of hospital construction, applications for positions and other administrative details; with Henry James (1913-July 1918) includes material for presentation at meetings of Board of Scientific Directors and its Executive Committee; with Acting Business Manager and with F. Dickey (1918-1919) and Edric B. Smith after 1921. Items of special interest are:
    Arrangement note
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - Letter to the Executive Committee from Dr. Cole asking approval to send Dr. Swift to Chicago to work for one week with Dr. Rosenau on the isolation of streptococcus, 1914 January 7 (Box 1)
    - Copy of form letter sent to New York physicians regarding interest in pneumonia patients for acceptance in Hospital's treatment program, [undated] (Box 1)
    - Letter from Alfred E. Cohn to Rufus Cole with data concerning the construction at Institute of Einthoven Galvanometer, 1914 March 26 (Box 1)
    - Letter to Henry James from Rufus Cole expressing concern over conditions for preparation. of pneumonia serum, 1915 September 23 (Box 1)
    - Copy of letter from Henry James to Rufus Cole covering October 20 the Resolution of Board of Scientific Directors to inform Surgeon General of ability and willingness to treat soldiers suffering from pneumonia at the Institute Hospital, 1917 October 23 (Box 1)
    - Memorandum concerning Publication of a New Journal to be undertaken by The Institute as proposed by Rufus Cole and presented at meeting of Scientific Directors, 1921 October (Box 1)
    - Later, the Board approved in principle, a subsidy provided suitable arrangements could be made, [ed. note: Probably resulted in Journal of clinical investigation], 1921 November 12 (Box 1)
    - Copy of letter from Alfred E. Smith, Governor and Matthias Nicoll, Commissioner of Health, thanking Dr. Cole for medical care given to Thomas F. Foley, 1925 January 16-23 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence on retirement of Dr. Cole and Minute adopted by Board of Trustees, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Photographs, 1911-1955; 1 folder (Box 1)
      33 photographs of Hospital staff. Some photos have identification.
    - Booklets prepared in 1977 for the Convocation at which honorary degrees were presented to Michael Heidelberger and Irvine Heinly Page (former members of Hospital staff) from archives photos (Box 1)
      Many identifications have been supplied.
    - Biographical materials, 1 folder (Box 1)
      Biographical materials including: [unreadable].
      - Copy from Who's Who; NAS Biographical Memoir, v. 50 pp 119-139
      - Reprint: The University Department of Medicine. Science n.s. 51 (1920) 329-340
      - Photographs (some with Hospital personnel)
      - Addresses made at retirement dinner, 1938 April 30
        Speakers: John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles R. Stockard, Herbert S. Gasser, Warfield T. Longcope, Thomas M. Rivers, Alfred E. Conn, Toastmaster.
      - Bibliography, 1901-1939
      - Correspondence, 1938-1951; 24 items
      - Human history, the 17th century and the Stuart family. Freeport, Maine, Bond Wheelwright Co., 1959; 2 bound volumes
    - Rough list of materials at American Philosophical Society where major portion of Rufus Cole papers are, 1983 (Box 1)
      Listing was supplied by Phillip Miller, M.D. [Feb 2 1983. G. Lewis in examining the 1 folder on Rufus Cole material found only listings of:.
      - Papers of dr. Rufus Cole: addresses and publications, 13 pp.
      - Additional papers of dr. Rufus Cole: addresses and publications, 2 pp.
      - Selected Papers by Dr. Cole, 2 pp.
        Includes handwritten note possibly by Philip Miller "The American Philosophical Society has most of these papers, and * M.C. Childs ([Mary C. Childs, Dr. Cole's daughter Mary]) has a copy".
    - 3 photogravures of Institute buildings, from the New York Architect, 1911 June (Package 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Entrance, Hospital building, Entrance, Laboratory building, Laboratory building.
    - Rockefeller Institute Dinner at the retirement of Rufus Cole. Radio and Film Methods Corp., 1938 April 30; Phonorecords. 33 1/3 speed, play from inside out. 1 package, 4 discs recorded on 7 sides.
      Conditions Governing Access
      RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
      Recording of speeches.
      - Side 1: Dr. Cohn and J.D. Rockefeller, Jr. (Package 2)
      - Side 2: J.D. Rockefeller, Jr. Dr. Cohn and Dr. Stockard (Package 2)
      - Side 3: Dr. Stockard, Dr. Cohn, Dr. Gasser (Package 2)
      - Side 4: Dr. Gasser, Dr. Cohn. Dr. Longcope (Package 2)
      - Side 5: Dr. Longcope, Dr. Cohn, Dr. Rivers (Package 2)
      - Side 6: Dr. Rivers, Dr. Cohn, Dr. Cole (Package 2)
      - Side 7: Dr. Cole (Package 2)
  - Alice Lockie, 1942-1968; 1 box
    Biographical/Historical note
    Alice Lockie was superintendent of the Rockefeller Institute Hospital from 1939/40 until her retirement in June 1969.
    These files were placed in the University archives by Miss Jo Armstrong on her retirement in June 1977.
    Arranged in alphabetical order
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Date received or inventoried: June 1977 (from Jo Armstrong).
    - Archibald, R.M. Correspondence, 1955-1964; 6 items (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Elliot, Roger. Correspondence, 1958-1965; 57 items (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Assorted administrative matters such as telephone usage; guards at entrances; emergency routines; snow removal schedules and some reports of accidents.
    - Guest Book of party. "Memories of Rockefeller Review" snapshots and notes of songs by hospital patients for the hospital staff, 1959 February 3 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Horsfall, Frank L. Correspondence, 1955-1960; 36 items (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Deals with titles, appointments, meetings on occupational therapy schedule changes
        Includes copy of 1971 obituary and draft of note sent with contributions from nursing and hospital staff.
      - NAS Biographical memoir 2, 50 pp. 233-267
    - Miscellaneous items (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Announcements of diseases under investigation, 1950/1951-1972/1973
      - Report of Committee on Hospital Affairs, 1957 October 28
      - List of staff attending weekly clinical conferences 4 Conference announcements, 1968 September
      - Invitation to reunion dinner to honor Alice N. Lockie on her retirement, 1969 June 20
      - Dr. M. McCarty to P. Penndorf on conversion of Rooms B3 and B3A to storage, 1974 September 26
    - Occupational Therapy Report Patience News no. 1 (August 10, 1960) to no. 4 (April 1965), 1962/1963 1965/1966; 1966/1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Patient care facility (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Floor plan of Hospital 3rd floor and 3rd floor North wing showing stations for patient care.
    - Rivers, Thomas M. Correspondence, 1942-1953; 9 items (Box 2, Folder 8)
      On spending nights in the hospital; consents for surgery on patients under 18 years of age. Letter from T. Debevoise.
    - Student Apartments lists and correspondence relating to furnishings of student apartments, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Tuberculosis Unit, 1953-1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Correspondence from Dr. Horsfall and James G. Hirsch on employee Tuberculin Testing Program. Includes lists of those tested and results as reported by Diethelm Böhme.